We're now ready to describe each of one of the blocks that built an image
我们现在要讲解建立图像压缩算法的每一个环节
compression algorithm and in particular, a JPEG.
而且会特别详细讲解静态图像压缩标准 (JPEG)
And as we say, we are going to start with a symbol encoder.
之前也提到过 我们将从符号编码器讲起
After we have basically done everything, we have done the transform and the
我们会对图像数据做变换和量化 这些环节在后续课程会详细讲解
quantization that we are going to explain in detail, we want to further compress.
在完成所有变换和量化之后 我们希望进一步压缩图像
So, quantization will provide us on compression that we want to further
量化会提供一定程度的压缩 但我们仍希望进一步压缩
compress. But we need to save whatever we have
我们需要存储量化后的数据
produced here. We need to save with no error.
我们需要保证精确无误地存储
But we're still going to see how we can compress.
但是也需要思考如何进行压缩
So, why can we achieve that? The basic idea is very simple.
那么 为什么能做到这些呢?  其基本思想很简单
And, of course, you can not teach image processing without showing that first, at
当然 如果不至少先给大家看一次这张叫 Lena 的非常著名的图片
least once, this famous image that is called Lena.
那就不算是教过图像处理
That it, it used to be used a lot in image processing.
在图像处理中 经常用到这张图片
But now, because of the abundance of images, many other images are used.
但现如今 由于我们拥有丰富的图像资源 也会使用许多其它图像
But I want to show it at least once during these, these nine weeks.
不过我还是想在这九周中至少给大家展示一次这张图片
And we might see the same image again a few more times.
而且在以后的课程中我们可能还会多次见到它
So, the basic idea is that some pixels, some gray values in the image appear more
基本思路是这样的 图像中的一些像素 一些灰度值出现的次数多于其它灰度值
than others. And let's see that.
我们来看看这个现象
Here on the right, we have what's called a histogram.
在右边 有一幅直方图
The histogram basically counts how many times a particular gray value appears in
直方图记录每一特定的灰度值在图像中出现的次数
the image. For example, the pixel value, the pixel
比如说 某一像素的灰度值
with gray values, let's say, around 47, appears this amount of times.
假设灰度值大约是47 它出现了这么多次
So, we go around the image, we count how many times I see the number 47 and this
我们遍历整幅图像 计算有多少灰度值为47的像素点
is the amount of times. Then I can go and see, for example, 200,
这就是它出现的次数 我们继续看下一个灰度值 比如说200
and I see this, this amount of time, about 700 times appears in the image.
我们看到 灰度值200在这幅图中大约出现了700次
So, we see that there are some pixels that appear a lot, there are some pixels,
我们可以看到有些像素值出现了许多次
let's say, zero or one don't appear at all.
而另一些像素值 比如 0或1 根本就没有出现过
And the basic idea that we are going to exploit is that we're going to try to
因此 我们要采用的方法的基本思路是
give to pixels, to pixels that appear a lot, very short course, and to pixel
给出现次数很多的像素值一个非常简短的编码
values that don't appear so much, we're going to try to give very long cause or
而给出现次数较少的像素值很长的 或者说相对较长的编码
longer course. Let's see how we do that.
下面来看看具体如何编码
Let's see an example of the use of this. So here, we have an image, and this is
下面来看一个应用上述方法的例子 这里是一个图像
actually the image that we saw in the previous video, the geometric image.
这正是大家在前面视频中见过的那个几何图像
This is a particular image that has, there's only four different gray values
这是比较特殊的图像 它只有四个不同的灰度值
in that image, and they appear, and so the pixels, pixels with gray value 87
而灰度值为87的像素占了整个图像的四分之一
appear in 1/4 on the image, so 25%,, 25% or probabilty of 0.25.
即 25% 或者说 灰度值47 出现的概率是 0.25
And we also have 128 appearing almost half of the time in the image, and we
同时灰度值为128的像素几乎占了图像的一半
also have 186 and 255 appears very, very few times, everybody else just doesn't
这里是灰度值186 而 255 出现的次数极少
appear in the image at all. So, the standard way to represent this
其它的灰度值并没有出现 所以表示这个图像的标准方式是
image is we have an array and for every pixel, we have a binary code with eight
用到了数组 对于每一个像素 使用八位二进制码表示其像素值
bits. So, we are going to basically represent
所以 我们用87的二进制码来表示灰度值87
87 with its binary representation. We are going to represent 128 with its,
用128的二进制码来表示灰度值128
its own binary representation and so on. So, at the end, we are basically spending
以此类推 所以在最后 如果我们不进行压缩
eight bits per pixel if we don't compress.
那每个像素要占 8比特
But let's assume that somehow I managed to basically construct a code that is
但是现在来假设一下 如果我想办法构造了如图所示的编码
shown here, in a way that 87 is represented by the
其中 87是用二进制码01来表示的
binary code 01, 128 is represented by the binary code
128 用二进制码1 来表示
one, 186 by the binary code 000 and 255 by the
186用二进制码000表示 而255用二进制码001
binary code 001. That means that, for example, if I want
这就意味着 比如说
to, if I want to store or send the pixels 87, 87,
如果想要存储或发送 87、87、255、128
255, 128.
这几个像素值
Instead of writing all these then, this again, for 255, this and for 128, this,
并不是用这些二进制码 然后是这个 而是用这个表示255 这些来表示128
which will take me basically, 4 times 8, 32 bits and I'm going to write it in the
这种表示方式需要 4乘以8 也就是32比特位 不如我们用以下这种方式来表示
following way. I'm going to say, okay,
我会假设
87 is 01. 87 again, 01.
87用01来表示 87还用01来表示
255, 001.
255用001来表示
128, 1. So, basically it took me two for seven,
128用1来表示 所以这里需要2 4 7
eight bits instead of 32 to represent the same stream the same form of gray values.
一共8比特 而不是32比特 来表示同一组灰度值
Now, the decoder has this table, so the decoder will see 01, we'll go into that
现在 解码器会根据这个表格解码 所以解码器看到01时
pixel position and we'll put an 87. We'll see 01, we'll put again an 87.
会在这个像素的位置输出 87 看到01 再次输出 87
We'll see 001, we say, oh, I need to put a 255, and so on.
然后发现 001 这里要输出255 等等
And so, we have achieved compression. Let's see exactly how much compression we
如此就完成了压缩 现在来看看这到底压缩了多少
can achieve. So basically, we do a very simple
我们来做一个非常简单的计算
computation. We say, okay, with probability zero
我们来看一看
point, sorry,
抱歉
with probability 0.25, I'm going to have length of 01,
我们有0.25的概率
a length of, of two. That's my, my code, 01.
需要用到长度为2的二进制码01
With probability 0.47, I'm going to have length of 1 plus 0.47 times one.
有0.47的概率 使用长度是1的二进制码 这里加上0.47乘以1
With probability 0.25, so for one quarter of the image, I'm going to have length
有0.25的概率 也就是四分之一的图像中 我们要用到长度为3的二进制码
three. And with very small probability, I'm also
最后是很小的概率
going to have length three. And this is equal to 1 60,
同样用到长度为3的二进制码 结果等于1.81
1.81. Okay.
好了
So, instead eight bits per pixel, I now have 1.81 on average on my whole image.
所以现在整个图像中平均每个像素只占1.81比特 而不是之前的8比特
I basically, I have save lots of pixels. Okay, I have gone from eight to basically
这里省了很多像素 从8减到了1.81
1.81. And that's a, that's a compression of
也就是说 压缩了四倍以上
over four times, and that's what we have done.
这就是我们刚刚做的
Basically, what we did is we have exploited the fact that some of the pixel
刚刚我们利用了一些像素值的出现次数远比另一些多的现象
values appear more often than others, and then I have to give shorter codes.
然后用更短的编码来表示这些像素值
I can give shorter codes. So, how we do that, we do that using
这里用了更短的编码 那么 怎么才能做到这一点呢
something which is called Huffman coding. And I'm going to explain next how to do
这里我们用到了霍夫曼编码 接下来我会解释怎么运用这种编码
it. So, lets just look once again in this
再看看这个例子
particular example, the best way to explain Huffman coding is just to use an
解释霍夫曼编码最好的办法是举个例子
example, and I'm going to that next. So, let's assume that we have five
接下来我要用这个例子说明 现在假设我们用五个不同的符号
different symbols, six different symbols, sorry.
抱歉 是六个不同的符号
And I order them, the first thing they have to do is order them with, according
第一步 按概率大小排列这些符号
to the probability. The highest probability first and the
概率从高到低
lowest probability at the end. And if some probabilities are equal, it
如果有些概率相同
doesn't matter which one we put first. So, for example, this symbol a2 might be
那么无所谓谁先谁后 比如说 a2可能代表像素值100
the pixel value 100. The symbol a6 might be the pixel value
符号 a6 可能代表像素值77 等等
77, and so on. So, I'm going to add,
现在我会做一些加法
basically I'm going to list the prob, the symbols here and the probabilities here.
先把符号列在这里 把概率列在这里
And from the bottom, I start to add. I take the two lowest.
然后从下往上 取最底下的两个数
And basically, I add their probabilities. So, I go from 0.04 plus 0.06 and that's
把它们的概率相加 用0.04加上0.06
probability one, 0.1. And then, I do the list again.
得到了0.1的概率 然后将这一列概率重新排列一遍
So, none of these has changed, the only one that changed is the last one.
这些都没有变 唯一改变了的是最后一个
See what's happening here. What's happening here is with probability
看看这里的变化 0.4的概率对应于a2
0.4, I can get a2, with probability 0.3, I can get a6, with probability 0.1, I can
0.3的概率指向a6 0.1的概率指向a1
get a1, with probability 0.1, I can get symbol
0.1的概率指向 符号 a4
a4, and with probability 0.1, I can get either a3 or a5.
而最后一个概率0.1对应a3或a5
I am going to have to do something to distinguish which one is it, is it a3 or
我们要用一些办法来区分 a3和a5
a5? And that's going to come in the next slide how we distinguish them.
下一张幻灯片会解释如何区分它们
Now, we do it, we do this again.
现在 重复一下刚才的步骤
We take the two lowest and then we add them.
将最低的两个值相加
And now, because it became 0.2, remember, we have to reorder all the time.
现在 这个值是0.2 记住每次都要重新排序
So, let me just describe that again. With 0.4, we can get a2.
让我再解释一下 概率0.4对应a2
With 0.3, we can get a6. Now, with 0.2, we can get either one of
0.3对应a6 而现在 0.2对应这两个概率值
these two, which is a4, a3 or a5.
也就是 a4、a3还有a5
I don't know which one but I know with 0.2 probability is one of them.
我们现在还不能确定是哪个符号 但是0.2的概率对应着其中一个
And then, we have 0.1 again. We do that once more, once more,
然后这里是0.1 重复刚才的步骤 再重复一次
actually, two more times. We have the two lowest.
实际上 还需要重复两次 我们得到这两个最小值
We get this and then we, once again, add it to lowest, and we get this.
算出这个值 再把它和最小的值相加 然后得到这个值
And once again, we, every time we add it to lowest and we move into the next
继续重复 每一次我们都将最小的两个值相加得到下一列概率值
column, we'll reorder everything. When we end up with only two, we stop.
并且重新排序 直到只剩下两个数
And we're going to see why we stop. Now, it's time to give the code.
然后来看看为什么在这里停下 下面我们来进行编码
So, basically, what I have done here, I basically redraw the graph that we have
这是依据前一幻灯片中图表的一个重绘
in the previous slide. And so, this is the first column, this is
这是第一列
the second column, and the third column, the fourth column, and the fifth column.
这是第二列 第三列 第四列 和第五列
And now, I'm going to go backwards, assigning codes.
现在 从后往前 依次赋值编码
So, basically to 0.6, I assigned zero. And to 0.4, I assigned one.
给0.6赋上0 给0.4赋上1
Before we go backwards, let me tell you what's happening.
在继续往回推进之前 我来解释一下这里是怎么回事
When the decoder is going to see a zero, it's going to know that it's from the
当解码器看到0 它会明白这是从 0.6对应的这一组来的
group that led to this 0.6. When you see sub one, it's going to know
当它看到一个 1
that it's from the group that leads to, lead to this 0.4.
就会知道是 0.4对应的这一组
Then we're going to have to keep adding bits to say which one in that group.
然后要添加更多的比特位来区分每组中的各个数值
And that's why we keep going backwards. So, we basically propagate back the zero.
这就是为什么要从后往前走 把这个 0 抄送到这里来
And we actually, the 0.6 came from 0.30.3, plus 0.3.
这个0.6是由 0.3加0.3 得来的
So, we add a zero and a one. So now we, of course, propagated 0.4 here
所以要在后面分别加上0和1 当然我们要把 0.4抄送到这里
and basically assigned it to this that came to this column, without adding any
给它赋上从上一列得来的码值 这里不用加任何数字
numbers. So, it keeps propagating without adding
所以它会一直不加任何比特位被抄送到前面
any bits. So now, all the symbols that lead to this
现在 要找到与这组对应的所有符号
group and we're going to see, it was actually only one symbol,
而这里 我们会看到 其实只有一个符号对应于这个组
we have this code and all the symbols that propagated to this probability.
现在有了这个编码和所有指向这个概率的符号
We have symbols that start, we have codes that start from 01.
这里的编码是从 01 开始的
So now, we keep propagating. We propagate the one to the one, the 00
现在继续往前抄送 将 1 抄送到这里 为1
to the 00. 01, we have to split because this 0.3
00 抄送为00 而01需要被分开因为这个0.3的概率
probability came from the addition of these two.
是由这两个相加得到的
And then, we have 010, 011. And then we keep going.
接着就变成了010和011 然后继续
The, we propagate the one to the one, the zero to the zero, this 010, which has a
把1抄送过来 0抄送过来 这个011的编码抄送到这里
code 011 propagates here. And this actually has to split.
而这个要分开
Every time we split because when we were computing it, we were adding.
每次之所以要把它分开 是因为之前在算它的时候是相加得到的
So, when we're going back, we were splitting.
然后回到这里 这里要分开
Every time we are splitting, we have to add zero and one.
每次分开的时候 都要加上0和1
And so, we keep going, we keep going, and we get this result that says that the
所以一直继续 就得到了这个结果
symbol 01 is going to have a code, one. The symbol 06 is going to have a code 00
也就是第一个符号的编码是1 符号a6的编码是00 以此类推
and so on. So, this is the code,
所以这就是它们的编码
it's a variable length code. Not every symbol is represented by a code
这些是变长编码 用来表示各个符号的编码长度并不完全一样
of the same length. It actually has a different length and
各个编码是有不同长度的
the length depends on the probability. The higher the probability, the shorter
而这个长度取决于概率 概率越大 编码越短
the code. And that's very easy to see because the
这很容易看出
low probabilities were added, added, added, added and then, when we're going
因为低概率值在不断被相加
back we have to split, split, split, split.
当往回推导的时候 就要不断分开
And remember, every time we split, we have to add a symbol, and we have to add
记住 每次分开的时候都要加一个符号 因此要为这个符号加一个比特位
a bit for that symbol. So, basically the code becomes longer and
所以 编码变得越来越长
longer. And we can actually go and compute, once
这里也可以算出编码的平均长度
again, the average length of these. So, to repeat the process, we basically
回顾一下之前的步骤
order the symbols according to the probability,
按照概率排列符号的顺序
that's what we did here. We start adding low probabilities.
这是这一步做的 然后开始把低概率相加
So, we add these two, we got this, we reorder and we keep going.
将这两个相加 就得到了这个 重新排列然后继续
It's a recursive process so if you know how to go from one column to the next,
这是一个递归的过程 所以如果知道了怎么从一列进行到下一列
you know how to go all the way. And then, we come back.
就知道了怎么完成它 然后回来看这个
There is a couple of things that are very important to observe here.
这里有几件非常重要的事情要注意
The code that you get in this way is what's called prefix-free.
用这种方法得到的编码叫做无前缀编码
And that's very, very important. Look at this column.
这是非常 非常重要的 来看这一列
When you see a one, when the decoder sees a one, it knows that it has to go here,
当这里有一个1 解码器看到一个1 它就知道要到这里找到a2
to a2. When is this a zero, it basically says,
当这里有一个0 这就是在说
okay, I have to wait for the next symbol. But there is no code here, which is a
好吧 我要等着看下一个符号是什么
full prefix of any other code. And that's very important, otherwise, the
但是没有任何一段码字完全是其它编码的前缀 这是非常重要的
decoder won't be able to reconstruct. Let's give an example of something which
不然解码器是无法重建图像的 看看下面这个例子
is not a prefix code. Let's say that the symbol a1 is
这里的码字会是前缀 比如 符号a1是用 码字1表示的
represented by the code one, the symbol a2 is represented by the code zero, and
符号 a2 是用 码字0 表示的
the symbol a3 is represented by the code 01,
符号a3 是用 码字01 表示的
okay? So, when the decoder sees 01,
当解码器看到01
basically there are two possibilities. It's either a3,
会出现两种可能 一种可能是a3
let's say, pixel value 100 or is a2 followed by a1.
假设它对应的像素值是100 另一种可能是 a2后面跟着a1
Let's say, pixel zero and pixel 255. So, there is a lot of ambiguity in the
假设像素是0和255 因此重建过程就出现了很大的歧义
reconstruction. We don't know which one it is.
无法分辨到底是哪一个
And this is because this code is not what's called prefix-free.
因为这个编码并不是无前缀编码
This guy is a subset of this guy. That doesn't happen here.
这个是这个的子集 而在这里就不会发生这种情况
Let's just clear these annotations. None of these codes,
现在把这些注释都清除
so for example, the 00, you don't find it anywhere here.
这里没有任何一个编码有所重复 比如说00
So, when the decoder sees a one, knows what to do.
因此 当解码器看到了一个1 就知道怎么办
It puts the pixel value of A2. When it sees a zero.
它会找到a2的像素值 当它看到一个0
Is it, oh, I'll have to wait, because there are many codes that starts with
它需要继续分辨 因为这里很多码字都是以 0 开头的
zero. If this is a zero, another zero and I'll
如果它看到有一个0 之后跟着一个0
say, oh, I'm done, I basically have a6. If, let's say, it's, so, the decoder
它会完成这段码字的解码 并得到a6
receives zero and then one, says, oh, I have to wait, because there are numerous
如果解码器收到了一个0 然后跟着一个1 它还需要继续分辨
codes that start with 01. But then, it receives an, a one.
因为有很多码字都是以01开头的 但是之后 如果又接收到了一个1
that says, oh, I'm done. I don't have to keep waiting.
它就完成了这段解码 不需要继续分辨了
Because there's nothing. There's no ambiguity here.
因为这里什么都没有 没有歧义
And that's very important, a Huffman code by construction.
这是非常重要的 霍夫曼码在构建时
Look how we basically, split, and split, and split.
我们这样一次又一次地进行分裂
And by construction, this is a prefix-free code.
它的构建过程 就决定了它是无前缀编码
Now, how do we know that this is an optimal code?
那么 如何得知它是最优编码方法呢？
How do we, how do we know that with this set of probabilities,
如何得知利用这组概率
the process, the procedure I just explained achieved the lowest possible
以及我刚刚解释的那个过程
the, the lowest possible length, the shortest possible length of a code on
就能达到最短的编码平均长度呢？
average. So, that's a theorem we have to prove,
这个定理有待证明
we're not going to do that in this class, but as a theorem that, that shows the
在这节课上我们不会涉及到这个证明 但是有一个定理
Huffman coding basically achieves the shortest possible length.
能够证明霍夫曼编码可以达到最短的长度
Now, you might wonder what length can Huffman coding achieve or any basically
现在 你可能会好奇霍夫曼编码 或者其它类似的编码器
encoder of this tile. So, the basic idea is if I give you a set
能达到的长度是多少 所以基本的思想是
of probabilities, how much can I compress?
当面对一组概率时 能够在多大程度上对其进行压缩？
How much, I go, and before I construct a Huffman code, I want to know, is it worth
在构建霍夫曼码之前 我们想要知道
the effort of constructing the code? Will I compress a lot?
这值不值得我们花费精力去构建这种编码？ 可以压缩很多吗？
And the way, the way to do that, is basically you compute what's called the
而这就要通过计算熵来得到答案
entropy. And the entropy,
熵使用符号 H 来表示
which is written by H, H is entropy,
H 就是指熵
[SOUND] is the sum over all the symbols with a minus here, I'm going to explain
熵是 所有符号的概率乘以该概率以2为底的对数 对所有乘积求和 再取负数
in a second, of the probability, of every symbol log base 2 of the probability of
关于这个负号 我等一下会解释
every symbol. So, it's basically sum, 0.4 times log
所以在这里就是 0.4 乘以 0.4以2为底的对数
base two of 0.4 plus 0.3 times log base two of 0.3 and so on.
加上0.3乘以 0.3以2为底的对数 依次类推
So, this is actually, at the end, a positive number because all probabilities
所以实际上最终得到的是一个正数
are below one and therefore, the log of the probabilities are negative numbers
因为所有概率都是小于1的 所以概率的对数是负数
and then with the negative, we get the positive.
加上这个负号 就会得到正数
And Shannon's First theorem basically says, that we can achieve basically,
香农第一定理就是在说
asymptotically, we can achieve this code length on average.
我们可以渐渐逼近这个平均编码长度
So, this is basically what's achievable with these types of codes, like Huffman
也就是像霍夫曼编码这类编码方式所能达到的 (最短长度)
code. We basically can compute this number and
可以来算算这个数
say, oh, that's going to be my average code length.
从而得到编码的平均长度
My expected average code length. And the, it's actually not so hard to
也就是理想的平均码长
understand where this formula comes from. We used a similar computation with the
实际上这个公式并不难理解
previous example. Here, the probability is basically the
之前的例子用过类似的计算
probability of the symbol appearing. And this is actually the length of the
这个概率就是符号出现的概率
code that is going to be used for that symbol.
而这是这个符号对应的编码长度
So basically, what this is saying is that the expected length of that code is the
这就是说 理想的编码长度就是这个概率的对数
log of the probability. And why it's only the expected is because
之所以是理想值是因为
you cannot have a code which is 3.2 long. You have to send entire bits.
编码长度不能是3.2 而只能发送完整的比特数
Either you send three bits or you send four bits.
或者发送 3比特 或者发送 4比特
And that's why this is on average the expectation,
这就是为什么 它是平均期望值
what you expect to be the code length. But this basically gives you an idea of
也即是编码长度的理想值
what encoders at Huffman coding can achieve.
但是这能帮助你理解霍夫曼编码的编码能力
So, now that we know how to encode the bits that we are producing, we are ready
现在大家已经知道如何用比特进行编码
to go into the next blocks of image compression.
我们要开始进入图像压缩的下一个模块了 //果壳教育无边界字幕组 | 冰之冷 | 某音某莹 | 林小七Lynn | 小白_远游